<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Health on raph haXx</title>
    <link>http://raph.es/tags/health/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Health on raph haXx</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Raphael Estrada 2011-2014</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2015 13:55:29 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://raph.es/tags/health/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>LCHF bread/cake base</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/blog/2015/03/low-carb-high-fat-lchf-cake-bread/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2015 13:55:29 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/blog/2015/03/low-carb-high-fat-lchf-cake-bread/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a little recipe I use to bake breads and cakes low in carbs and high in fat - without wheat or sugar. The below describes the base which results in a bread-like loaf. By adding spices or sweetener or whatever you like you can easily modify it to your taste, including sweet cake or muffins by throwing in your sweetener of choice. You can even modify it to make pancakes, pizza dough etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most recipes for &amp;ldquo;low carb bread&amp;rdquo; you will find online try to be high in protein but low in fat. This here is my adaptation which is still medium to high in protein but also has a high fat content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;output-size:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Output size&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exact amounts depend on the size of your baking pan. I usually use a tray about 3cm deep, lined with baking paper (I prefer the re-usable silicon variant). The below makes a full oven-wide and oven-deep tray of about 2-3cm high bread/cake. You will have to try and tweak to get optimal results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nuts-and-seeds:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Nuts and seeds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The eggs and nuts are what give the bread it&amp;rsquo;s form. I use different nuts every time - whatever is around the kitchen - but they should be mostly ground (not necessarily to a flour, although that can help). You can buy them pre-ground or throw them into a food processor and gring yourself - the sky is the limit. Seeds also absorb water so they can help make the bread firm. Leave some chunky bits in if you like that. Here are just some of the things I typically throw in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;flax seed (whole or ground)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;coconut (dessicated or flour)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;chia seeds (whole)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pumpkin seeds (whole)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sunflower seeds (whole)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sesame seeds (whole)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;peanuts (chopped or ground)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;walnuts (chopped or ground)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;macadamia nuts (chopped or ground)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;brazil nuts (chopped or ground)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;psyllium husks (entire husks)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;protein-powder:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Protein powder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get good results when using protein powder to stiffen up the dough but I tend to use it lightly to not at all, nuts taste better and work fine. For smaller loafs and bread buns you might want to experiment with bigger amounts of protein powder, it helps a lot. Just make sure to get some that tastes neutral and is low in carbs, but high in protein and not full of sugar or other weird chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;ingredients:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll split this up into essential base ingredients and then list some things you can throw in to taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;base:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Base&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8-10 eggs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;100+ml whipping cream&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;100+g butter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon baking powder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20+g coconut oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;150+g various ground nuts and/or seeds (see above)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20g psyllium husks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;optional-to-taste:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Optional, to taste&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;100+g Xylitol or sweetener of choice (for sweet bread or cakes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protein powder (for firmer dough, e.g. when making buns)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peanut butter, or other nut butters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cocoa (powder or chunks)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cream cheese&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very dark chocolate (at least 85% cocoa)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One or more shots of espresso&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Berries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Salt, spices, tiny splash of vinegar (for bread variety)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grated cheese&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fried onions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bits of veggies, e.g. tomato, broccoli, cauliflower&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avocado&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;hellip;your imagination is the limit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;preparation:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not much science here, just mix it all together, maybe starting with the molten butter, eggs and cream to get them stirred up well. Add the nuts and other ingredients. You will know that the ratio of ingredients is right when the dough is a firm goo - I prefer it to still wobble and move a bit. Be careful to not make it too sticky, especially if you&amp;rsquo;re working with protein powder. Let the dough stand for at least fifteen minutes to let seeds soak and the dough to firm up. Mix a bit every now and then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pour into pan lined with baking paper (or form buns with thicker dough if that&amp;rsquo;s what you&amp;rsquo;re going for). Stick into preheated oven at around 160 degrees Celsius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the dough heats during baking, it will soften and flow together - that&amp;rsquo;s perfect for the pan, but if you want little buns and want to prevent them from becoming one large goop then make the dough stiffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bake four at least 20 minutes. Keep an eye on it every five minutes or so. Duration in oven will depend on how liquid your dough was and how high your pan is. For my pan it&amp;rsquo;s usually a bit more than 20 mins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you poke the dough and see that nothing sticks you can turn off the oven and let it stand in the remaining heat until the oven cools.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The bias is strong with MBTI</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/blog/2014/10/bias-is-strong-with-mbti/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2014 12:51:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/blog/2014/10/bias-is-strong-with-mbti/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, at work, I took a personality test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a three day course, and the whole team participated. Early on, we took a twenty-minute test and added up the scores to end up with four numbers. Each number tells you where you sit one of four linear scales. Each scale is split through the middle and - depending on which half your number falls on - you get one of two letters per scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting four letters combine to form your &lt;em&gt;Myers-Briggs Type Indicator&lt;/em&gt; (MBTI). By knowing someone&amp;rsquo;s MBTI, you&amp;rsquo;re supposed to be able to better predict and understand another&amp;rsquo;s preferences and behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Enterprise&amp;rdquo; loves MBTI because of how it puts people into neatly labelled boxes. Consultants love MBTI because enterprise loves MBTI. Which is why I was sitting in said course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;i-got-intp:4d381c0f3550be0df929f1ee1b3291eb&#34;&gt;I got &lt;code&gt;INTP&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;I&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;i&lt;/strong&gt;ntroverted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;N&lt;/code&gt;: i&lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;tuitive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;T&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;t&lt;/strong&gt;hinking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;P&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;p&lt;/strong&gt;erceiving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be honest and admit that when I began writing this, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t even remember what the last three stood for. I had to refresh my memory on Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;25-science:4d381c0f3550be0df929f1ee1b3291eb&#34;&gt;25% science.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome on the first scale can either be &lt;strong&gt;i&lt;/strong&gt;ntrovert or &lt;strong&gt;e&lt;/strong&gt;xtrovert. In our group, this scale seemed to yield the clearest results. Given that most attendees were software developers, it should come as no surprise that most of us ended up getting &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? There&amp;rsquo;s a large body of research and a variety of literature on the introvert-extrovert spectrum. Software development is consistently described as a field that attracts introverts. So I&amp;rsquo;m going to let this one pass as it&amp;rsquo;s both scientificallly grounded and relevant in day-to-day life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t reiterate what is already well-described in aforementioned books. But just to give one example, it&amp;rsquo;s why many of us prefer the asynchronous nature of electronic means of communication (i.e. email, chat) over synchronous face-to-face &amp;ldquo;talk&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;75-percent-bullshit:4d381c0f3550be0df929f1ee1b3291eb&#34;&gt;75% percent bullshit.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My beef with the other three is not that they don&amp;rsquo;t apply to me. Quite the opposite actually. It&amp;rsquo;s because they are defined in such a way that they apply to &lt;em&gt;everybody&lt;/em&gt; and are inherently context dependant. Testing for them only captures one&amp;rsquo;s preference &lt;em&gt;at the time of the test&lt;/em&gt;, under the conditions of the test. But under different circumstances I might as well come out as the polar opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one point we were presented with a hypothetical scenario: you are the coach of a children&amp;rsquo;s football club. You manage to get just two tickets for a big game. How to do you decide who goes, and how do you communicate that to the children?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to MBTI, a typical &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;t&lt;/strong&gt;hinker&lt;/em&gt; would rank kids by some level of skill and reward the best with the tickets. A &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;f&lt;/strong&gt;eeler&lt;/em&gt; would be more worried about the other kids being sad or dissapointed, and try to work out a more social solution with the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem here is, &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt; are polar opposites of the same scale. I was scored to be a strong &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; based on the questions in the test earlier. And yes, the thought of ranking the kids by their dedication to the club did cross my mind. But I was just as concerned about the other kids being dissapointed as the next &lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had suggested alternatives, one being to take all the other kids to another event rather than not rewarding them at all. However, they depended on variables not provided. The scenario - being part of a pre-defined course programme -  was contrived in order to set the stage for the purposes of MBTI. It lacked much information which would have influenced my solution. Like the number of children, their age, the price of tickets vs family income&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But alternatives weren&amp;rsquo;t part of the programme. The trainer made the point she had come to make. And I learned that there is no room for alternatives in the littlle boxes which are MBTI (stereo)types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;life-is-not-linear:4d381c0f3550be0df929f1ee1b3291eb&#34;&gt;Life is not linear.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A linear scale is simply not sufficient to accomodate this spectrum of decision making. Flattening it all like MBTI does disposes too much information to have relevance in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I was to be generous (which apprarenltly I&amp;rsquo;m not, because I&amp;rsquo;m not a &lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;) I could admit that MBTI gave a correct prediction that I had &lt;em&gt;considered&lt;/em&gt; the ranking option, and as a result &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; have decided something similar. But that&amp;rsquo;s pretty thin, and practically impossible to disprove.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When people end up doing what MBTI predicted, it appears to confirm the correctness of MBTI. When people decide differently, it&amp;rsquo;s either ignored or handwaived away by the general cop-out:&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;MBTI only describes a preference&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See also: &lt;em&gt;confirmation bias&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did raise my concerns during the course. The defense was the same every time. Our &amp;ldquo;trainer&amp;rdquo; would argue that MBTI merely describes a &lt;em&gt;preference&lt;/em&gt;, not a general rule (huge red flag). I might have agreed if people hadn&amp;rsquo;t instantly fell into a pattern of reducing others to their scores. &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;P&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt; do &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; while &lt;em&gt;J&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt; do &lt;code&gt;y&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rdquo;, the trainer would say. So even if we gave MBTI the benefit of the doubt, and went with the &lt;em&gt;preference&lt;/em&gt; hypothesis, in practice it is not used as such. Human minds don&amp;rsquo;t work like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of us wore their score like a badge. Literally: many wrote their scores in big letters onto the name signs in front of them. Gradually, people with similar scores formed little teams. In what superficially appeared to be innocent fun, teams ganged up and mocked the others&amp;rsquo; MBTI-stereotypes. &amp;ldquo;Haha, you &lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt; be so crazy.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See also: &lt;a href=&#34;http://therearenoothers.wordpress.com/2011/12/28/othering-101-what-is-othering/&#34;&gt;othering&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;pseudo-science-is-pseudo:4d381c0f3550be0df929f1ee1b3291eb&#34;&gt;Pseudo-science is pseudo.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sixteen MBTI type profiles are strangely reminiscent of zodiac signs. They are written in such a way that they could apply to anybody. After we got the hard-earned score, we had a chance to read all profiles. At this point we had already been told what we &amp;ldquo;are&amp;rdquo;, and our minds were already set to read other profiles as if they didn&amp;rsquo;t match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect if we had been given the profiles without any prior labelling, it would have been very difficult to find a single one that matches. People would have identified with different profiles under different circumstances. People are not one-dimensional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fine print states MBTI is just a preference, but the scores quickly become comfortable boxes. Once you&amp;rsquo;re convinced that you are an &lt;em&gt;XXXX&lt;/em&gt;, you identify with it so much that you become it. When a situation arises that seems to fit the profile, it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;wow, that&amp;rsquo;s obviously because I&amp;rsquo;m X!&amp;rdquo;. When the profile is at odds with behaviour, it is brushed off as an outlier and ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See also: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astrology_and_science&#34;&gt;astrology&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See also: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pseudoscience&#34;&gt;pseudo-science&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-is-mbti-so-popular-then:4d381c0f3550be0df929f1ee1b3291eb&#34;&gt;Why is MBTI so popular then?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people enjoy taking personality tests and sharing the outcome. We are quick to identify with the results, especially when they confirm our expectations. Just look at how successful pseudo-scientific tests are in magazine&amp;rsquo;s or social media (i.e. Facebook). MBTI tests or derivatives thereof are very popular on the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s easy to do the test. And passing a test gives you a sense of accomplishment. It&amp;rsquo;s fun to label oneself and others. It&amp;rsquo;s fun to make fun people&amp;rsquo;s quirks. It makes sense on the surface and contains just enough science to make it get past our bullshit sensors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I buy into the introvert-extrovert spectrum, but the rest is too dynamic for anyone to have a meaningful score. MBTI has very little practical relevance. It oversimplifies human psychology and the complexity of decision making. The resulting simplicity is what makes it so tempting to buy into MBTI. I think it&amp;rsquo;s dangerous how it sets wrong expectations when people use it as a predictor. Which they do, despite the disclaimers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, looking at all this I suppose I&amp;rsquo;m a typical &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Or am I?)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alcohol sucks</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/blog/2014/10/why-i-dont-drink-alcohol/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2014 17:35:48 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/blog/2014/10/why-i-dont-drink-alcohol/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I spent my teen and early adult life in southern Germany. The area is world famous for it&amp;rsquo;s beer. And alcohol is deeply ingrained in German culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some years ago - to the surprise of many of my family and friends - I decided to stop drinking alcohol for good. You wouldn&amp;rsquo;t believe how much ridicule I was confronted with. It&amp;rsquo;s scary how prevalent alcohol is in everyday life - something that you only really see when you attempt to avoid it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;people-ask-if-i-m-a-recovering-alcoholic:10bcf212d78158276a87c5caad077679&#34;&gt;People ask if I&amp;rsquo;m a recovering alcoholic.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I answer no, although answering yes would be easier. It seems like being an alcoholic is the only acceptable reason to not drink for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Society respects the &lt;em&gt;recovering alcoholic&lt;/em&gt;, who has ventured so far into boozeland. Like they crossed some bizarre finish line. Mission accomplished. It&amp;rsquo;s a way of proving one&amp;rsquo;s ability to hold even more alcohol than the other guy. An impressive achievement, apparently. Just listen to friends and family credit each other for how much they were able to drink at that wedding last weekend. For being so hung over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A subtle difference compared to the &lt;em&gt;dedicated driver&lt;/em&gt;: the hero-for-a-night who takes on the burden of seeing how stupid his friends behave when they get intoxicated. But only under the condition that someone else drives the next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To clarify my reasoning, I thought I&amp;rsquo;d write a little list of pros and cons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;drinking-alcohol-cons:10bcf212d78158276a87c5caad077679&#34;&gt;Drinking alcohol CONS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;- costs a lot of money
- tastes horrible
- it&#39;s literally toxic
- is bad for my health
- makes me fat
- makes me feel sick
- gives me a headache the next day
- lowers my intelligence
- makes me more likely to do dumb things
- prevents me from driving
- decreases my ability to defend myself in case of an attack
- increases the chances of being attacked
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, don&amp;rsquo;t you tell me alcohol doen&amp;rsquo;t taste horrible. It&amp;rsquo;s barely drinkable even when masked by other ingredients (malt, barley in beer; sugar in wine and cocktails). Higher concentrations taste so bad, people frown and gag when they drink it. The only people who enjoy it are either pretending in order to appear tough or maybe alcoholics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, if you drink the stuff long enough, you&amp;rsquo;ll learn to distinguish tastes. Some drinks will taste better than others. Just because it doesn&amp;rsquo;t taste terrible doen&amp;rsquo;st mean it tastes good. Objectively, alcohol tastes bad and for a good reason: because it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;toxic&lt;/em&gt;. Our body doesn&amp;rsquo;t want it, so we haven&amp;rsquo;t evolved to get any reward for drinking it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, moving on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;drinking-alcohol-pros:10bcf212d78158276a87c5caad077679&#34;&gt;Drinking alcohol PROS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;+ complies with social norms
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There you have it. Most of us grow up around adults who drink. We observe and learn that it&amp;rsquo;s what adults are supposed to do in certan situations. It&amp;rsquo;s a social habit that we copy and never question. And which many people make fun of when someone refuses to play along (I know because I&amp;rsquo;m that someone).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you didn&amp;rsquo;t know, I&amp;rsquo;m an &lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/on/introverts&#34;&gt;introvert&lt;/a&gt;. I don&amp;rsquo;t enjoy pubs and nights out. With the privilege of hindsight I now understand that the main reason I spent a significant part of my youth going to pubs and drinking alcohol was because I was under the impression that it&amp;rsquo;s what you&amp;rsquo;re supposed to do. And to impress friends. &lt;em&gt;Girls&lt;/em&gt; even.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sounds &lt;em&gt;incredibly silly&lt;/em&gt;. And it is. Which is why I stopped! I can socialize without drinking alcohol. I will not perpetuate the synthetic importance of an expensive toxin. Especiallly not to my kids. Oh, and I&amp;rsquo;m beyond the point where I think I have to impress people like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My kids will grow up with me as an example for how you can think for yourself and refuse to do stupid stuff other people do. How you don&amp;rsquo;t have to be a recovering alcoholic to stop drinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most or all of the above could also be said about smoking. If you don&amp;rsquo;t smoke, you probably shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be drinking for the same reason. Smoking is bad for you? Tastes horrible? Expensive? An excuse to socialize with other smokers? A bad example for kids? Check, check, check, check, check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;em&gt;that guy&lt;/em&gt; who orders a pot of tea at the bar. I&amp;rsquo;m don&amp;rsquo;t do so because I &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to drive. I&amp;rsquo;m the dedicated driver because I don&amp;rsquo;t drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get over it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;update-2015-07-17:10bcf212d78158276a87c5caad077679&#34;&gt;Update (2015-07-17):&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just found a recent xkcd comic which happens to go with this post remarkably well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        xkcd.com: **Beer**
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;http://xkcd.com/1534/&#34;&gt;Randall Munroe&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://xkcd.com/1534/&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/beer.png&#34;  alt=&#34;Mmmm, this is such a positive experience! I feel no social pressure to enjoy it at all!&#34;   /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>