<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>raph haXx</title>
    <link>http://raph.es/</link>
    <description>Recent content on raph haXx</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Raphael Estrada 2011-2016</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2015 16:25:31 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://raph.es/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>LCHF Nuremberger Elisenlebkuchen</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/blog/2015/12/low-carb-high-fat-lchf-nuernberger-nuremberger-elisen-lebkuchen/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2015 16:25:31 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/blog/2015/12/low-carb-high-fat-lchf-nuernberger-nuremberger-elisen-lebkuchen/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/oldschool.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/oldschool_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;*Lebküchner* from an illustrated manuscript in the Stadtbibliothek Nürnberg, ca. 1520&#34; style=&#34;width: 300px;&#34;  /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Premium old-school *Lebkuchen* are naturally low in carbs
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lebkuchen&#34;&gt;en.wikipedia: Lebkuchen&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I&amp;rsquo;d like to share the recipe for my low-carb-high-fat (and by extension, gluten and sugar-free) variant of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.germanfoodguide.com/lebkuchen.cfm&#34;&gt;Nuremberger Elisenlebkuchen&lt;/a&gt;. You can find variations of &lt;em&gt;Lebkuchen&lt;/em&gt; all over Germany (and beyond), but the one I present here is based on an original, old-school recipe straight from the source: Nuremberg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, the best Lebkuchen are those with the highest possible nuts-to-flour ratio. This is unlike the cheaper ones you can find in supermarkets and Christmas markets all over the world, which contain more flour and sugar than nuts. The original recipes favour nuts over flour and starch; a perfectly reasonable definition of &amp;ldquo;premium&amp;rdquo; to me, and taken further, gives you the ideal LCHF treat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Src: &lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/N%C3%BCrnberger_Lebkuchen&#34;&gt;Wikipedia.de&lt;/a&gt;; Translated to English by me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Als besonderes Qualitätsmerkmal gilt ein hoher Anteil von Mandel- und Nusskernen und eine geringe Zugabe von Mehl oder sogar der völlige Verzicht darauf. [&amp;hellip;] Oblatenlebkuchen der höchsten Qualität gemäß Deutschem Lebensmittelbuch heißen „Elisenlebkuchen“ und nehmen bei praktisch allen Nürnberger Anbietern einen prominenten Platz im Sortiment ein; sie müssen eine besonders hochwertige Zusammensetzung mit mindestens 25% Mandeln, Haselnüssen oder Walnüssen aufweisen, dürfen keine anderen Ölsamen und maximal 10% Mehl oder 7,5% Stärke enthalten.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A special quality characteristic is a high content of almond and nut kernels and minimal addition - or even avoidance of - flour. [&amp;hellip;] According to the German Food Guide, &amp;lsquo;Oblatenlebkuchen&amp;rsquo; of the highest quality are called &amp;lsquo;Elisenlebkuchen&amp;rsquo; and take a prominent position within the range of products offered by Nuremberg&amp;rsquo;s producers; they must have a particularly high-quality composition of at least 25% almonds, hazelnuts or walnuts, may not contain other oilseeds and at most 10% flour or 7.5% starch.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing this, I cranked up the nut contents to nearly 100% - which according to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.germanfoodguide.com/lebkuchen.cfm&#34;&gt;German Food Guide&lt;/a&gt; technically qualifies as the most premium Lebkuchen one can possibly make, all the while being low in carbs and high in good fats and fibre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s only two ingredients in the original Elisen-Lebkuchen which are bad carb-offenders:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Oblate&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;: a little tasteless wafer that holds the cake. You can just leave this out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The sugar&lt;/strong&gt;: (duh) which can easily be replaced with alternative sweeteners such as Xylitol or Stevia.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/oblaten.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/oblaten_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Picture of *oblaten* wafers.&#34; style=&#34;width: 300px;&#34;  /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Oblaten are basically cardboard. Would you eat cardboard?
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;requirements:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 eggs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;200g ground raw almonds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;200g ground raw hazelnuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15g psyllium husks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Xmas-y spices (cinnamon, nutmeg, cloves, allspice, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cocoa powder (100%, unsweetened)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lemon juice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baking powder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~30g thick cut diabetic orange marmalade (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~50g Xylitol (optional) or your preferred sweetener&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This yields more or less 1 large baking tray, or ~20 medium Lebkuchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;implementation:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;Implementation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, the steps are easy. It&amp;rsquo;s the spices and sweetening where I recommend you take some time and taste your way through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;short-version:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;Short version&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix nuts, eggs, psyllium husks, baking powder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add some cinnamon, cloves, cocoa, orange peel, lemon juice to taste&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sweeten using orange marmalade and/or Xylitol&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bake for 15 minutes, let cool&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;long-version:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;Long version&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-easy-bit:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;The easy bit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whisk together: nuts, eggs and psyllium husks. Add a dash of baking powder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-dash-of-christmas:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;A dash of Christmas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are Christmas treats, so add the usual suspects: cinnamon, nutmeg, cloves, anise, allspice - whatever floats your boat. I don&amp;rsquo;t mind using off-the-shelf &amp;ldquo;Christmas Spice&amp;rdquo; mixes, because I&amp;rsquo;m lazy. You can find dedicated &amp;ldquo;Lebkuchen&amp;rdquo; spice mixes, too - but those often contain sugar and wheat, so make sure you understand what you are buying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add a large spoonful of cocoa powder to the mix. Or more if you like. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t darken very much. Be careful to not add too much, it can make the dough bitter and you might find yourself adding more sweetener at the end to balance it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-orangeat-problem:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Orangeat&lt;/em&gt; problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lebkuchen traditionally contain &lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orangeat&#34;&gt;Orangeat&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zitronat&#34;&gt;Zitronat&lt;/a&gt;, which translates to candied orange and lemon peel. This is what happens when people soak bitter food in sugar because - apparently - everything has to taste sweet in order to taste good (or so the logic seems to go).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Candied&amp;rdquo; == sugar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy you choose to sweeten your Lebkuchen depends on how sweet you like your treats to be (if at all), and then what kind of sugar alternatives you prefer. You can start off entirely un-sweet by using some actual (&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; candied) orange and lemon peel, then sweeten the whole thing afterwards to taste. But be careful, you can come out on the very bitter end, which isn&amp;rsquo;t everybody&amp;rsquo;s thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;rsquo;t really go wrong with a splash or two of pure lemon juice to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I then tend to do is add one or two big spoonfuls of thick-cut diabetic orange marmalade. This adds the slightly bitter orange taste and also a bit of sweet, which I can subtract from the Xylitol I would otherwise have added later. The brands I can find in my area are sweetened with sugar alcohols (Sorbitol or Maltritol), which isn&amp;rsquo;t as good as Xylitol, but still beats aspartame by a mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/marmalade.jpg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/marmalade_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Picture of *oblaten* wafers.&#34; style=&#34;width: 300px;&#34;  /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Diabetic marmalades are usually sweetened with sugar alcohols.
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stute-foods.com/itemlist.php?clasrefr=CatRef2&#34;&gt;Stute&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I strongly recommend you take your time and gradually add very little sweet and give it a taste. Stop when it tastes sweet enough - &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; add a final tiny dash of sweet. The sweet taste tends to go away a bit during the baking process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However: There is no shame in err&amp;rsquo;ing on the less-sweet side. I find it more than sufficient to have the Lebkuchen only subtly sweet, leaving room for the other spices and nuts to come through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;drying-not-baking:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;Drying, not baking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put baking paper (or the fancy silicon stuff) onto a baking tray. Using a large spoon, distribute blobs of the dough onto the tray. Leave a bit of space between them, but don&amp;rsquo;t worry about them melting or otherwise growing much - there&amp;rsquo;s not much butter or cream in the recipe, so they should pretty much stay put.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re not going to bake these like you would bake a cake. Just heat them up to dry a little bit, then let &amp;lsquo;em cool. I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have to point this out, but&amp;hellip; the longer you dry them, the drier they will be. I prefer them rather moist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stick it into the (pre-heated) oven at 120 degrees Celsius for about 12-15 minutes. Take out the tray and let them cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/one.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/one_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Close up of one Lebkuchen I made this way.&#34; style=&#34;width: 450px;&#34;  /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/many.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/many_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Picture of several Lebkuchen I recently made.&#34; style=&#34;width: 450px;&#34;  /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Ta-dah!
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;mixing-it-up:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;Mixing it up&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional Lebkuchen contain almonds, hazelnuts and/or walnuts. But that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you can&amp;rsquo;t use other kinds of nuts! I like to use macadamia and brazil nuts. Dessicated &lt;em&gt;coconut&lt;/em&gt;, even. Go crazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, you can experiment with the spices. I recommend trying less sweetener and more cinnamon and cocoa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you so desire you can glaze them with chocolate. I usually just melt high-cocoa sugar-free chocolate with some coconut oil and spread that on top. This part is optional and up to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just be careful adding any liquids such as cream or butter/oils which can turn liquid in the oven. Your Lebkuchen might melt when heated. Best leave these out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;references:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lebkuchen&#34;&gt;en.wikipedia: Lebkuchen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/N%C3%BCrnberger_Lebkuchen&#34;&gt;de.wikipedia: Nuernberger Lebkuchen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lebkuchengew%C3%BCrz&#34;&gt;de.wikipedia: Lebkuchengewuerz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;www.germanfoodguide.com/lebkuchen.cfm&#34;&gt;German Food Guide: Lebkuchen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lebkuchen-schmidt.com/en/&#34;&gt;Lebkuchen Schmidt&lt;/a&gt; - where I used to buy Lebkuchen online from abroad before I ditched carbs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>hack-o-lantern</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/project/hack-o-lantern/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2015 19:10:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/project/hack-o-lantern/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Of course we put an Arduino Mini with some LEDs into a fierce looking pumpkin for Halloween.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/hackolantern/portrait.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/hackolantern/portrait_thumb.jpeg&#34;     /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>the world needs zita the spacegirl</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/blog/2015/07/the-world-needs-zita-the-spacegirl/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2015 22:41:47 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/blog/2015/07/the-world-needs-zita-the-spacegirl/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A steady stream of superhero flicks keeps tearing up the box office and whatever is left of television programmes, with no &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Marvel_Cinematic_Universe_films#Future&#34;&gt;end&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DC_Comics%27_shared_universe_films#Future&#34;&gt;sight&lt;/a&gt;. For kids trapped inside adult bodies like me, this is the best time to be alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/marvel-phase3.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/marvel-phase3_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Marvel MCU phase 3  movie announcements until 2019&#34;   /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Enjoy the comic craze while it lasts
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.modernmythmedia.com/2014/11/marvel-releases-phase-3-timeline-poster&#34;&gt;Modern Myth Media&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nerdstalgia aside, I&amp;rsquo;m also a parent. And as such I am very critical of the media I expose my children to. Lot of junk is being thrown at kids. I will try not to get stuck in a rant about the rampant sexism and capitalist brainwashing present in so-called children&amp;rsquo;s entertainment - that&amp;rsquo;s for another post. Suffice to say for now that I have an aggressive bullshit filter for things I let through to my children&amp;rsquo;s sensitive brains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;fear-not:0ca3f1610d7d19fe7fd7e0429d0e5a3b&#34;&gt;Fear not!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/graphic-novel.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/graphic-novel_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Dr. Evil from the film Austin Powers making quotes with his fingers, saying Graphic Novel&#34;   /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all is lost. Some people are making really good, progressive comics (also known by their grown-up name: &lt;em&gt;graphic novels&lt;/em&gt;). I&amp;rsquo;d like to highlight one such gem right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://zitaspacegirl.com&#34;&gt;Zita The Spacegirl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; began as a &lt;a href=&#34;http://zitaspacegirl.com/webcomics&#34;&gt;web comic&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.benhatke.com&#34;&gt;Ben Hatke&lt;/a&gt;. Hatke later set out to tell Zita&amp;rsquo;s origin story in the form of a paperback &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/8879121-zita-the-spacegirl&#34;&gt;trilogy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zita&amp;rsquo;s adventure begins with her best friend Joseph being kidnapped by a creepy alien thing - and it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Zita&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt; fault. That&amp;rsquo;s some serious drama right off the bat. Just because it&amp;rsquo;s a story for children, doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean it has to be fluffy kittens, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s spaceships, lasers and explosions - albeit never excessively violent. The plot is not as &lt;del&gt;lame&lt;/del&gt; predictable as many other books in the children&amp;rsquo;s section would be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/zita/spacegirl.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/zita/spacegirl_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Cover of the graphic novel Zita The Spacegirl&#34; style=&#34;width: 50%;&#34;  /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;video&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe class=&#34;vimeo-player&#34; type=&#34;text/html&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/16484045&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        The stakes are high, even on page one.
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;http://zitaspacegirl.com&#34;&gt;Ben Hatke&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The illustrations are excellent. Hatke obviously knows how to do composition and lighting, and uses his skills well. Space is a dark place, yet the story is mostly bright and colourful. The odd dark moment never crosses into nightmare-inducing territory. The story has depth, but never gets too complicated and doesn&amp;rsquo;t need much explaining in order for kids to follow along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing, drawing, inking, lettering - Hatke did virtually everything himself, and mostly by hand. Especially the sketchy line art gives the story a personal touch, making no attempt to hide that this story is being told by a human being. And that with some practice, kids could do something like it, too. The sketches included at the end of each book further show how much fun (and work) Hatke poured into them, for adults and kids to appreciate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/zita/sketches.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/zita/sketches_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Sketches at the back of a Zita book&#34; style=&#34;width: 150%;&#34;  /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;http://us.macmillan.com/books/9781596434462&#34;&gt;First Second Books&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;subliminal-messages:0ca3f1610d7d19fe7fd7e0429d0e5a3b&#34;&gt;Subliminal messages&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides being easy on the eyes, what really makes the Zita books special is the characters. They are fresh, loveable and relatable. Hatke avoids most of the overused tropes we have all become so used to from mainstream comics. He tackles difficult topics such as responsibility, tolerance, sacrifice - even &lt;em&gt;slavery&lt;/em&gt; - in sensitive, tasteful ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world is full of details and feels organic and alive. Many characters appear in just a few panels, yet have distinct memorable personalities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/zita/consequences.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/zita/consequences_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Zita is charged with crimes in a court.&#34; style=&#34;width: 120%;&#34;  /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Zita faces the consequences of her actions
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;http://us.macmillan.com/books/9781596434462&#34;&gt;First Second Books&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/zita/dop.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/zita/dop_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Dop is a character from the Zita books.&#34; style=&#34;width: 120%;&#34;  /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/zita/detail.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/zita/detail_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Little detail characters are everywhere in the books&#34; style=&#34;width: 120%;&#34;  /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Dop is one of our favorite characters.
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;http://us.macmillan.com/books/9781596434462&#34;&gt;First Second Books&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;diversity:0ca3f1610d7d19fe7fd7e0429d0e5a3b&#34;&gt;Diversity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One pet hate of mine is when entertainment - especially they kind supposedly made for children - deploys and perpetuates anti-social sterotypes. It&amp;rsquo;s taking creative shortcuts, resulting not just in less interesting stories but also sending outdated and essentially &lt;em&gt;harmful&lt;/em&gt; messages to children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comics in particular have a terrible track record when it comes to diversifying race and gender. The good news is that Zita fairs very well in both regards. The four central humanoid protagonists consist of two males and two females. Three of them are white. But considering how all the other characters are literally &lt;em&gt;aliens&lt;/em&gt; - many of whom play important roles in the story - there is certainly no shortage of racial diversity within the Zita universe. Interestingly, all antagonists are aliens. Hatke successfully dodged &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; bullet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I tend to write adventurous female protagonists, but that’s probably &lt;strong&gt;because it’s what I’m surrounded by&lt;/strong&gt; in my day-to-day life. I have four kick-ass daughters and a badass lady friend. If I need inspiration I just watch what they’re doing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&amp;ndash;Ben Hatke; @&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickeringmyth.com/2014/11/girl-power-ben-hatke-talks-return-zita-spacegirl.html&#34;&gt;flickeringmyth.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;objectification-or-lack-thereof:0ca3f1610d7d19fe7fd7e0429d0e5a3b&#34;&gt;Objectification (or lack thereof)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite things about the Zita books is that none of the characters are overly sexualized. It&amp;rsquo;s one of those things you suddenly become aware of when you are the father to daughters. Everywhere girls look, they are presented with incredibly unrealistic and unnatural images of women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/monster-high.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/monster-high_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Monster high dolls by Mattel&#34;   /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        My best guess is they starved to death.
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monster_High#/media/File:Monster_High_dolls.jpg&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zita&amp;rsquo;s female physique is not exaggerarated in any sexual way, and it&amp;rsquo;s bizzare that I even have to point that out. Her interactions with other characters have nothing to do with her being a girl. For instance, her relationship to Joseph is never romantic. It&amp;rsquo;s a friendship where one person just happens to be female.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/psylocke.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/psylocke_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Marvel ninja Psylocke dressed in tight latext&#34; style=&#34;width: 130%;&#34;  /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        This is not how ninjas dress
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickeringmyth.com/2015/06/olivia-munn-shows-off-psylockes-sword-skills-for-x-men-apocalypse.html/psylocke&#34;&gt;flickeringmyth.com&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, so Zita is a little girl. Let&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;pretend&lt;/em&gt; for a moment that even the most twisted, misogynistic artist wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have objectified this character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exhibit B: Madrigal, the adult female. She&amp;rsquo;s a badass pirate, and a lesser artist could have easily portrayed here as a scantily-clad space babe. The Madrigal Hatke gives us is mature and attractive, but not because she wears tight/slutty/barely any clothes. Instead, what she wears is a reflection of her own character. She wears comfortable, practical clothes. She has tatoos. It&amp;rsquo;s convincingly the style of a confident woman who likes to express herself, as opposed to the premature wet dream of some white male artist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;// TODO RAPH: picture of madrigal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of equality, I find it important to emphasize that it&amp;rsquo;s not just the female characters which are free of the usual comic stereotypes. The males are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; testosterone-drenched muscle-packed warriors, but normal, flawed human beings with feelings. Joseph initially needs saving by Zita, a welcome twist on the Damsel In Distress trope. Piper has no discernable super powers other than his intelligence and paranoia. And get this: his weapon of choice is a flute. Not a gun. Not a sword. &lt;em&gt;Music&lt;/em&gt;. The language of the soul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;it’s impossible &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; to sexualise [comic] characters&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Axel Alonso; Marvel editor-in-chief; src: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/women/womens-life/11071016/Marvel-comic-book-editor-I-wont-say-no-to-sexy-female-superheroes.-Comics-still-need-to-be-naughty-and-fun.html&#34;&gt;The Telegraph&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;3:0ca3f1610d7d19fe7fd7e0429d0e5a3b&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;3&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me conclude by saying that I really think the world needs more comics like Zita The Spacegirl. Not only because it passes the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bechdel_test&#34;&gt;Bechdel Test&lt;/a&gt;. But because, at it&amp;rsquo;s core, it&amp;rsquo;s about love and respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/zita/zita-love.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/zita/zita-love_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Zita bridges language barrier with alien though hugging&#34; style=&#34;width: 120%;&#34;  /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        (click for full strip)
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;http://zitaspacegirl.com/webcomics-2/&#34;&gt;Ben Hatke&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hatke has hinted that there might be more Zita comics in the future. If so, I cannot wait to throw my money at it. I also really hope that Zita will inspire other authors to make high quality, progressive graphic novels which are compatible with adults&amp;rsquo; and childrens&amp;rsquo; minds alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of me would really love to see this made into a film. Then again, it feels like Zita is just perfect as a graphic novel, and any form of reinterpretation might do more harm than good. It &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt;, however, make for an awesome video game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a more practical point of view, you can get the complete story in three inexpensive books. This means you can introduce children to a comic that has a beinning, a middle and an end without much trouble. Sure beats trying to catch up on literally &lt;em&gt;hundreds&lt;/em&gt; of inherently inconsistent issues of Spider-Man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I’m hoping to one day create a second trilogy [and some short stories]. However Zita will be a few years older when we see her again.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&amp;ndash;Ben Hatke; @&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickeringmyth.com/2014/11/girl-power-ben-hatke-talks-return-zita-spacegirl.html&#34;&gt;flickeringmyth.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>kids-cosplay</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/project/zita/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2015 13:01:25 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/project/zita/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Inspired by videos of cosplayers online, my daughter set out to make a Zita costume. Zita is rather on the simple side as cosplay goes, making it ideal as a first project of this kind. And if the pictures of Zita costumes on Hatke&amp;rsquo;s blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.benhatke.com/2014/10/a-halloween-post-with-trick-and-treat.html&#34;&gt;are&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.benhatke.com/2013/11/the-great-zita-spacegirl-costume-parade_5.html&#34;&gt;any&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.benhatke.com/2013/11/the-great-zita-spacegirl-costume-parade.html&#34;&gt;indication&lt;/a&gt;, we aren&amp;rsquo;t the first fans to work on a costume, either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/zita/spacegirl.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/zita/spacegirl_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Cover of the graphic novel Zita The Spacegirl&#34;   /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        The world needs more heroes like Zita.
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;http://us.macmillan.com/books/9781596434462&#34;&gt;First Second Books&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took only a few hours from finding the right materials to stitching everything together. I encouraged her to document the process and write up a little recap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon after, we also made an Enderman costume for my son from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of them showcased their outfits at MCM Comic Con in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/cosplay/zita.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/cosplay/zita_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Zita the Spacegirl costume&#34;   /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/cosplay/enderman.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/cosplay/enderman_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Minecraft Engerman costume&#34;   /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;video&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe class=&#34;youtube-player&#34; type=&#34;text/html&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/lmlrr47NGmI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;
 &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Kids cosplay is the best type of cosplay
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bleedingcool.com/2014/11/06/when-kids-cosplay-at-new-york-comic-con-video/&#34;&gt;BleedingCool.com&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I made a retro game console for the kids</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/blog/2015/07/retropie-game-emulator-kids-raspberry-pi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2015 10:48:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/blog/2015/07/retropie-game-emulator-kids-raspberry-pi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I often behave like a I am still just a kid, only with more than five bucks allowance. As such, I somtimes spend unreasonable money on gimmicks and gadgets based solely on the awesome things I &lt;em&gt;imagine&lt;/em&gt; I can use them for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/retropi/buy-things.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/retropi/buy-things_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;When I go into a buying rage for no mature reason whatsoever.&#34; style=&#34;width: 20em;&#34;  /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Steam sales are the worst.
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;http://hyperboleandahalf.blogspot.ie/2010/06/this-is-why-ill-never-be-adult.html&#34;&gt;Allie Brosh&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reality catches up eventually, and in one such case I found myself with several spare Raspberry Pi computers in my Command Centre (aka &amp;ldquo;where we hang the clothes to dry&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I figured I could spare one for the kids. To justify my spending but also because the Pi was designed to educate children. And if first-world kids lack education in any subject, then that&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Old Video Games Nobody Plays Anymore&lt;/em&gt;. Obviously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Born in the early eighties, I am among the first generation of kids to grow up with video games being just a normal thing. Anyone before us met electronic games as a newfangled imitation of other forms of entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/retropi/cryengine.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/retropi/cryengine_thumb.jpeg&#34;   style=&#34;width: 25em;&#34;  /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Modern game engines produce ridiculously realistic visuals.
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;http://assets.crytek.com/asset-bank/action/viewAsset?id=2120&#34;&gt;Crytek Press Release&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kids today grow up with flashy graphics and epic soundtracks. Technically, they are amazing. But gameplay is not always on par. Older games had to work with many more constraints. And constraints foster creativity in important ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, finding good modern games for kids is not as easy as you might expect. Most of the plethora of mobile games are full of ads, in-app purchases or are designed around a single mind-numbing, yet addictive mechanic for more generic appeal. Or all of the above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some notable exceptions exist, of course. Like &lt;em&gt;Minecraft&lt;/em&gt;, which ironically was never designed with kids in mind but turns out to be mind-boggingly successful with young players. Parents all over the world try to understand their childrens&amp;rsquo; fascination with Minecraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/retropi/stampy.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/retropi/stampy_thumb.jpeg&#34;   style=&#34;width: 25em;&#34;  /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Gazillions of kids watch *stampy* play Minecraft on YouTube.
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/stampylonghead&#34;&gt;stampylonghead&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Console games for kids are not much better. Most are either badly executed, too difficult or simply not appropriate for smaller kids. Many of the best console games seem innocent enough but have violent mechanics at their core. They are made &lt;em&gt;by&lt;/em&gt; and made &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; cash-strapped ex-children like myself, not &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my offspring is still traumatized from that time we tried out the demo of &lt;em&gt;Castle Crashers&lt;/em&gt;. Granted, I could have noticed the PEGI 18, but for fuck&amp;rsquo;s sake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;video&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe class=&#34;youtube-player&#34; type=&#34;text/html&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/BsLHvg93bX4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;
 &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        It&amp;#39;s cute. It&amp;#39;s fun. It&amp;#39;s all about murdering things.
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t pretend to believe that the majority of games - new or old - don&amp;rsquo;t have destructive mechanics at their centre. Shoot, beat and kill-em-ups have been around since day one. But with their blocky graphics and chirpy sounds, &lt;del&gt;old&lt;/del&gt; retro games couldn&amp;rsquo;t even be scary if they tried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how they tried. Doom, for instance, scared the shit out of me at the time. But even that is comically dated by today&amp;rsquo;s standards. The more immersive modern games become, the more I feel they can have unintended negative effects, particulaly on young brains. The next wave of Virtual Reality gizmos is on the horizon, and you might want to hold off from plugging your kids into them for just a little while, just sayin&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With literally thousands of games to choose from, very low system requirements, and technical limitations so severe that catchy gameplay is almost guaranteed, retro games make the perfect choice for kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we have a retro console using a Pi, and I will tell you how we did it. In a later post. See you there!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>xkcd comments on alcohol</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/blog/2015/07/xkcd-comic-makes-my-point-on-alcohol/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2015 18:55:48 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/blog/2015/07/xkcd-comic-makes-my-point-on-alcohol/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just found a recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xkcd.com&#34;&gt;xkcd&lt;/a&gt; comic which happens to express my stance &lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/on/alcohol&#34;&gt;on alcohol&lt;/a&gt; remarkably well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://xkcd.com/1534/&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/beer.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Comic figure gets peer-pressured into enjoying beer.&#34; style=&#34;width: 600px;&#34;  /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        I feel no social pressure to enjoy it at all!
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;http://xkcd.com/1534/&#34;&gt;Randall Munroe&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LCHF bread/cake base</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/blog/2015/03/low-carb-high-fat-lchf-cake-bread/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2015 13:55:29 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/blog/2015/03/low-carb-high-fat-lchf-cake-bread/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a little recipe I use to bake breads and cakes low in carbs and high in fat - without wheat or sugar. The below describes the base which results in a bread-like loaf. By adding spices or sweetener or whatever you like you can easily modify it to your taste, including sweet cake or muffins by throwing in your sweetener of choice. You can even modify it to make pancakes, pizza dough etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most recipes for &amp;ldquo;low carb bread&amp;rdquo; you will find online try to be high in protein but low in fat. This here is my adaptation which is still medium to high in protein but also has a high fat content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;output-size:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Output size&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exact amounts depend on the size of your baking pan. I usually use a tray about 3cm deep, lined with baking paper (I prefer the re-usable silicon variant). The below makes a full oven-wide and oven-deep tray of about 2-3cm high bread/cake. You will have to try and tweak to get optimal results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nuts-and-seeds:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Nuts and seeds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The eggs and nuts are what give the bread it&amp;rsquo;s form. I use different nuts every time - whatever is around the kitchen - but they should be mostly ground (not necessarily to a flour, although that can help). You can buy them pre-ground or throw them into a food processor and gring yourself - the sky is the limit. Seeds also absorb water so they can help make the bread firm. Leave some chunky bits in if you like that. Here are just some of the things I typically throw in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;flax seed (whole or ground)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;coconut (dessicated or flour)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;chia seeds (whole)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pumpkin seeds (whole)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sunflower seeds (whole)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sesame seeds (whole)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;peanuts (chopped or ground)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;walnuts (chopped or ground)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;macadamia nuts (chopped or ground)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;brazil nuts (chopped or ground)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;psyllium husks (entire husks)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;protein-powder:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Protein powder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get good results when using protein powder to stiffen up the dough but I tend to use it lightly to not at all, nuts taste better and work fine. For smaller loafs and bread buns you might want to experiment with bigger amounts of protein powder, it helps a lot. Just make sure to get some that tastes neutral and is low in carbs, but high in protein and not full of sugar or other weird chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;ingredients:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll split this up into essential base ingredients and then list some things you can throw in to taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;base:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Base&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8-10 eggs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;100+ml whipping cream&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;100+g butter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon baking powder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20+g coconut oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;150+g various ground nuts and/or seeds (see above)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20g psyllium husks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;optional-to-taste:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Optional, to taste&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;100+g Xylitol or sweetener of choice (for sweet bread or cakes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protein powder (for firmer dough, e.g. when making buns)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peanut butter, or other nut butters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cocoa (powder or chunks)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cream cheese&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very dark chocolate (at least 85% cocoa)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One or more shots of espresso&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Berries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Salt, spices, tiny splash of vinegar (for bread variety)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grated cheese&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fried onions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bits of veggies, e.g. tomato, broccoli, cauliflower&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avocado&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;hellip;your imagination is the limit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;preparation:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not much science here, just mix it all together, maybe starting with the molten butter, eggs and cream to get them stirred up well. Add the nuts and other ingredients. You will know that the ratio of ingredients is right when the dough is a firm goo - I prefer it to still wobble and move a bit. Be careful to not make it too sticky, especially if you&amp;rsquo;re working with protein powder. Let the dough stand for at least fifteen minutes to let seeds soak and the dough to firm up. Mix a bit every now and then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pour into pan lined with baking paper (or form buns with thicker dough if that&amp;rsquo;s what you&amp;rsquo;re going for). Stick into preheated oven at around 160 degrees Celsius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the dough heats during baking, it will soften and flow together - that&amp;rsquo;s perfect for the pan, but if you want little buns and want to prevent them from becoming one large goop then make the dough stiffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bake four at least 20 minutes. Keep an eye on it every five minutes or so. Duration in oven will depend on how liquid your dough was and how high your pan is. For my pan it&amp;rsquo;s usually a bit more than 20 mins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you poke the dough and see that nothing sticks you can turn off the oven and let it stand in the remaining heat until the oven cools.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This website</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/project/website/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2014 21:00:59 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/project/website/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;requirements:6483546648f978b66ffde57bc20bcb3b&#34;&gt;requirements&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;simple-tech:6483546648f978b66ffde57bc20bcb3b&#34;&gt;Simple tech&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;static pages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;no database&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;simple style&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;no social media spyware&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;no tracking pixels or anything&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NO JAVASCRIPT AT ALL, all html/css/img&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;personal:6483546648f978b66ffde57bc20bcb3b&#34;&gt;personal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my own design from the ground up - incl all quiks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reflect all my activity on side-projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;minimal use of social media, link to my page to channel output through here&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;playgrund to screw around with web tech - it&amp;rsquo;s my own and i can hack it however i like&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my own domains&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;shorter-posts:6483546648f978b66ffde57bc20bcb3b&#34;&gt;Shorter posts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;half twitter, half blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;occasional long post (like this one)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;incremental value - projects, series aggregate nr of small posts to bigger context&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;no-comments:6483546648f978b66ffde57bc20bcb3b&#34;&gt;No comments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;see also: simple tech&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;no spam, no trolls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;drop me a mail if you have something to say&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;libre:6483546648f978b66ffde57bc20bcb3b&#34;&gt;libre&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;open source (static pages are by definition)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hosted on github&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;open source license (DECIDE: gpl  or Creative Commons?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;programmer-s-workflow:6483546648f978b66ffde57bc20bcb3b&#34;&gt;Programmer&amp;rsquo;s workflow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;github&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;command line tools (hugo, git, nano)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;content in simple text / markdown editing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;automatic delivery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;todo:6483546648f978b66ffde57bc20bcb3b&#34;&gt;TODO&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;continuous delivery downside: parallel travis workers -&amp;gt; race condition, not atomic pushes&lt;/del&gt; &amp;ldquo;fixed&amp;rdquo; by limiting travis to one single concurrent build at a time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TOC shortcode?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GitHub issues for content improvements/changes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;show revision of source repo as version in subtree html&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;embed history/versions of a given content?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;highlight currently selected menu section&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;auto-deploy from tavis to github pages&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;stale projects where date &amp;gt; x&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;highlight latest blog posts, projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;shrinkify pngs for project, way to large&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;watermark images&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add project pages, i.e. software ones

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dansguardian&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;nodewire&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;gogre3d, llcoi&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;gorf24&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;next/prev content by date&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;style code snippets better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;license page  &amp;ldquo;/license&amp;rdquo;&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new domain with DNS config&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;cv&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MudCam HD</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/project/mudcam/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2014 08:21:11 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/project/mudcam/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I thought it would be neat to build a (nearly) disposable video cam to wear on mudruns - where stuff gets wet, dirty, broken and lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My progress so far stopped as I was figuring out the power questions when using a Raspberry Pi (v1) on a battery. The newer RPi versions look much better for crunching video but they fare probably a lot worse power-wise. If I pick this up again, I&amp;rsquo;ll probably stick with the Model A I began with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;materials:70b8ce9c723897901564e89eb06c922f&#34;&gt;Materials&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raspberry Pi Model A + Camera module&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MCP 1826S 3.3V voltage regulator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IP-66 waterproof junction box&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Waterproof cable glands&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Airsoft replica MICH helmet with rails&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~30cm HDMI cable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 CSI breakout connectors to hook up HDMI cables to Pi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Waterproof momentary switch with LED ring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2000mAh - 3000m+Ah single-cell 3.7C LiPo battery (e.g. for tablets)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The bias is strong with MBTI</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/blog/2014/10/bias-is-strong-with-mbti/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2014 12:51:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/blog/2014/10/bias-is-strong-with-mbti/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, at work, I took a personality test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a three day course, and the whole team participated. Early on, we took a twenty-minute test and added up the scores to end up with four numbers. Each number tells you where you sit one of four linear scales. Each scale is split through the middle and - depending on which half your number falls on - you get one of two letters per scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting four letters combine to form your &lt;em&gt;Myers-Briggs Type Indicator&lt;/em&gt; (MBTI). By knowing someone&amp;rsquo;s MBTI, you&amp;rsquo;re supposed to be able to better predict and understand another&amp;rsquo;s preferences and behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Enterprise&amp;rdquo; loves MBTI because of how it puts people into neatly labelled boxes. Consultants love MBTI because enterprise loves MBTI. Which is why I was sitting in said course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;i-got-intp:4d381c0f3550be0df929f1ee1b3291eb&#34;&gt;I got &lt;code&gt;INTP&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;I&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;i&lt;/strong&gt;ntroverted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;N&lt;/code&gt;: i&lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;tuitive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;T&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;t&lt;/strong&gt;hinking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;P&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;p&lt;/strong&gt;erceiving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be honest and admit that when I began writing this, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t even remember what the last three stood for. I had to refresh my memory on Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;25-science:4d381c0f3550be0df929f1ee1b3291eb&#34;&gt;25% science.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome on the first scale can either be &lt;strong&gt;i&lt;/strong&gt;ntrovert or &lt;strong&gt;e&lt;/strong&gt;xtrovert. In our group, this scale seemed to yield the clearest results. Given that most attendees were software developers, it should come as no surprise that most of us ended up getting &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? There&amp;rsquo;s a large body of research and a variety of literature on the introvert-extrovert spectrum. Software development is consistently described as a field that attracts introverts. So I&amp;rsquo;m going to let this one pass as it&amp;rsquo;s both scientificallly grounded and relevant in day-to-day life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t reiterate what is already well-described in aforementioned books. But just to give one example, it&amp;rsquo;s why many of us prefer the asynchronous nature of electronic means of communication (i.e. email, chat) over synchronous face-to-face &amp;ldquo;talk&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;75-percent-bullshit:4d381c0f3550be0df929f1ee1b3291eb&#34;&gt;75% percent bullshit.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My beef with the other three is not that they don&amp;rsquo;t apply to me. Quite the opposite actually. It&amp;rsquo;s because they are defined in such a way that they apply to &lt;em&gt;everybody&lt;/em&gt; and are inherently context dependant. Testing for them only captures one&amp;rsquo;s preference &lt;em&gt;at the time of the test&lt;/em&gt;, under the conditions of the test. But under different circumstances I might as well come out as the polar opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one point we were presented with a hypothetical scenario: you are the coach of a children&amp;rsquo;s football club. You manage to get just two tickets for a big game. How to do you decide who goes, and how do you communicate that to the children?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to MBTI, a typical &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;t&lt;/strong&gt;hinker&lt;/em&gt; would rank kids by some level of skill and reward the best with the tickets. A &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;f&lt;/strong&gt;eeler&lt;/em&gt; would be more worried about the other kids being sad or dissapointed, and try to work out a more social solution with the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem here is, &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt; are polar opposites of the same scale. I was scored to be a strong &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; based on the questions in the test earlier. And yes, the thought of ranking the kids by their dedication to the club did cross my mind. But I was just as concerned about the other kids being dissapointed as the next &lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had suggested alternatives, one being to take all the other kids to another event rather than not rewarding them at all. However, they depended on variables not provided. The scenario - being part of a pre-defined course programme -  was contrived in order to set the stage for the purposes of MBTI. It lacked much information which would have influenced my solution. Like the number of children, their age, the price of tickets vs family income&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But alternatives weren&amp;rsquo;t part of the programme. The trainer made the point she had come to make. And I learned that there is no room for alternatives in the littlle boxes which are MBTI (stereo)types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;life-is-not-linear:4d381c0f3550be0df929f1ee1b3291eb&#34;&gt;Life is not linear.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A linear scale is simply not sufficient to accomodate this spectrum of decision making. Flattening it all like MBTI does disposes too much information to have relevance in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I was to be generous (which apprarenltly I&amp;rsquo;m not, because I&amp;rsquo;m not a &lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;) I could admit that MBTI gave a correct prediction that I had &lt;em&gt;considered&lt;/em&gt; the ranking option, and as a result &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; have decided something similar. But that&amp;rsquo;s pretty thin, and practically impossible to disprove.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When people end up doing what MBTI predicted, it appears to confirm the correctness of MBTI. When people decide differently, it&amp;rsquo;s either ignored or handwaived away by the general cop-out:&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;MBTI only describes a preference&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See also: &lt;em&gt;confirmation bias&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did raise my concerns during the course. The defense was the same every time. Our &amp;ldquo;trainer&amp;rdquo; would argue that MBTI merely describes a &lt;em&gt;preference&lt;/em&gt;, not a general rule (huge red flag). I might have agreed if people hadn&amp;rsquo;t instantly fell into a pattern of reducing others to their scores. &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;P&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt; do &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; while &lt;em&gt;J&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt; do &lt;code&gt;y&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rdquo;, the trainer would say. So even if we gave MBTI the benefit of the doubt, and went with the &lt;em&gt;preference&lt;/em&gt; hypothesis, in practice it is not used as such. Human minds don&amp;rsquo;t work like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of us wore their score like a badge. Literally: many wrote their scores in big letters onto the name signs in front of them. Gradually, people with similar scores formed little teams. In what superficially appeared to be innocent fun, teams ganged up and mocked the others&amp;rsquo; MBTI-stereotypes. &amp;ldquo;Haha, you &lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt; be so crazy.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See also: &lt;a href=&#34;http://therearenoothers.wordpress.com/2011/12/28/othering-101-what-is-othering/&#34;&gt;othering&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;pseudo-science-is-pseudo:4d381c0f3550be0df929f1ee1b3291eb&#34;&gt;Pseudo-science is pseudo.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sixteen MBTI type profiles are strangely reminiscent of zodiac signs. They are written in such a way that they could apply to anybody. After we got the hard-earned score, we had a chance to read all profiles. At this point we had already been told what we &amp;ldquo;are&amp;rdquo;, and our minds were already set to read other profiles as if they didn&amp;rsquo;t match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect if we had been given the profiles without any prior labelling, it would have been very difficult to find a single one that matches. People would have identified with different profiles under different circumstances. People are not one-dimensional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fine print states MBTI is just a preference, but the scores quickly become comfortable boxes. Once you&amp;rsquo;re convinced that you are an &lt;em&gt;XXXX&lt;/em&gt;, you identify with it so much that you become it. When a situation arises that seems to fit the profile, it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;wow, that&amp;rsquo;s obviously because I&amp;rsquo;m X!&amp;rdquo;. When the profile is at odds with behaviour, it is brushed off as an outlier and ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See also: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astrology_and_science&#34;&gt;astrology&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See also: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pseudoscience&#34;&gt;pseudo-science&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-is-mbti-so-popular-then:4d381c0f3550be0df929f1ee1b3291eb&#34;&gt;Why is MBTI so popular then?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people enjoy taking personality tests and sharing the outcome. We are quick to identify with the results, especially when they confirm our expectations. Just look at how successful pseudo-scientific tests are in magazine&amp;rsquo;s or social media (i.e. Facebook). MBTI tests or derivatives thereof are very popular on the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s easy to do the test. And passing a test gives you a sense of accomplishment. It&amp;rsquo;s fun to label oneself and others. It&amp;rsquo;s fun to make fun people&amp;rsquo;s quirks. It makes sense on the surface and contains just enough science to make it get past our bullshit sensors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I buy into the introvert-extrovert spectrum, but the rest is too dynamic for anyone to have a meaningful score. MBTI has very little practical relevance. It oversimplifies human psychology and the complexity of decision making. The resulting simplicity is what makes it so tempting to buy into MBTI. I think it&amp;rsquo;s dangerous how it sets wrong expectations when people use it as a predictor. Which they do, despite the disclaimers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, looking at all this I suppose I&amp;rsquo;m a typical &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Or am I?)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schoolbag bling</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/project/bagsbling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2014 08:20:17 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/project/bagsbling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a first wearables project we geeked up the kids&amp;rsquo; schoolbags by adding animated LED motifs to them. One red/yellow heart and one blue/white flashing lightning bolt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/bagsbling/bling-heart.gif&#34;  alt=&#34;The heart-shaped LEDs flash on and off.&#34;   /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/project/bagsbling/bling-lightning.gif&#34;  alt=&#34;The lightning-shaped LEDs flash on and off.&#34;   /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because nothing says &amp;ldquo;too cool for school&amp;rdquo; like MCU-driven LED backpacks do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TKD trainer</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/project/tkdtrainer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2014 08:21:06 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/project/tkdtrainer/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alcohol sucks</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/blog/2014/10/why-i-dont-drink-alcohol/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2014 17:35:48 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/blog/2014/10/why-i-dont-drink-alcohol/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I spent my teen and early adult life in southern Germany. The area is world famous for it&amp;rsquo;s beer. And alcohol is deeply ingrained in German culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some years ago - to the surprise of many of my family and friends - I decided to stop drinking alcohol for good. You wouldn&amp;rsquo;t believe how much ridicule I was confronted with. It&amp;rsquo;s scary how prevalent alcohol is in everyday life - something that you only really see when you attempt to avoid it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;people-ask-if-i-m-a-recovering-alcoholic:10bcf212d78158276a87c5caad077679&#34;&gt;People ask if I&amp;rsquo;m a recovering alcoholic.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I answer no, although answering yes would be easier. It seems like being an alcoholic is the only acceptable reason to not drink for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Society respects the &lt;em&gt;recovering alcoholic&lt;/em&gt;, who has ventured so far into boozeland. Like they crossed some bizarre finish line. Mission accomplished. It&amp;rsquo;s a way of proving one&amp;rsquo;s ability to hold even more alcohol than the other guy. An impressive achievement, apparently. Just listen to friends and family credit each other for how much they were able to drink at that wedding last weekend. For being so hung over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A subtle difference compared to the &lt;em&gt;dedicated driver&lt;/em&gt;: the hero-for-a-night who takes on the burden of seeing how stupid his friends behave when they get intoxicated. But only under the condition that someone else drives the next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To clarify my reasoning, I thought I&amp;rsquo;d write a little list of pros and cons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;drinking-alcohol-cons:10bcf212d78158276a87c5caad077679&#34;&gt;Drinking alcohol CONS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;- costs a lot of money
- tastes horrible
- it&#39;s literally toxic
- is bad for my health
- makes me fat
- makes me feel sick
- gives me a headache the next day
- lowers my intelligence
- makes me more likely to do dumb things
- prevents me from driving
- decreases my ability to defend myself in case of an attack
- increases the chances of being attacked
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, don&amp;rsquo;t you tell me alcohol doen&amp;rsquo;t taste horrible. It&amp;rsquo;s barely drinkable even when masked by other ingredients (malt, barley in beer; sugar in wine and cocktails). Higher concentrations taste so bad, people frown and gag when they drink it. The only people who enjoy it are either pretending in order to appear tough or maybe alcoholics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, if you drink the stuff long enough, you&amp;rsquo;ll learn to distinguish tastes. Some drinks will taste better than others. Just because it doesn&amp;rsquo;t taste terrible doen&amp;rsquo;st mean it tastes good. Objectively, alcohol tastes bad and for a good reason: because it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;toxic&lt;/em&gt;. Our body doesn&amp;rsquo;t want it, so we haven&amp;rsquo;t evolved to get any reward for drinking it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, moving on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;drinking-alcohol-pros:10bcf212d78158276a87c5caad077679&#34;&gt;Drinking alcohol PROS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;+ complies with social norms
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There you have it. Most of us grow up around adults who drink. We observe and learn that it&amp;rsquo;s what adults are supposed to do in certan situations. It&amp;rsquo;s a social habit that we copy and never question. And which many people make fun of when someone refuses to play along (I know because I&amp;rsquo;m that someone).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you didn&amp;rsquo;t know, I&amp;rsquo;m an &lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/on/introverts&#34;&gt;introvert&lt;/a&gt;. I don&amp;rsquo;t enjoy pubs and nights out. With the privilege of hindsight I now understand that the main reason I spent a significant part of my youth going to pubs and drinking alcohol was because I was under the impression that it&amp;rsquo;s what you&amp;rsquo;re supposed to do. And to impress friends. &lt;em&gt;Girls&lt;/em&gt; even.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sounds &lt;em&gt;incredibly silly&lt;/em&gt;. And it is. Which is why I stopped! I can socialize without drinking alcohol. I will not perpetuate the synthetic importance of an expensive toxin. Especiallly not to my kids. Oh, and I&amp;rsquo;m beyond the point where I think I have to impress people like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My kids will grow up with me as an example for how you can think for yourself and refuse to do stupid stuff other people do. How you don&amp;rsquo;t have to be a recovering alcoholic to stop drinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most or all of the above could also be said about smoking. If you don&amp;rsquo;t smoke, you probably shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be drinking for the same reason. Smoking is bad for you? Tastes horrible? Expensive? An excuse to socialize with other smokers? A bad example for kids? Check, check, check, check, check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;em&gt;that guy&lt;/em&gt; who orders a pot of tea at the bar. I&amp;rsquo;m don&amp;rsquo;t do so because I &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to drive. I&amp;rsquo;m the dedicated driver because I don&amp;rsquo;t drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get over it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3d business card</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/project/3d-card/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2014 08:26:47 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/project/3d-card/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It would be cool to design a business card and print it with a 3D printer. Experimenting with the haptics of the card and the related typography could be interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>on blogging</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/blog/2014/10/on-blogging/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2014 17:32:23 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/blog/2014/10/on-blogging/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not known to be an early adopter. I was late to the party for blogs with my &lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/blog/2011/02/just-do-it/&#34;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; attempt ocurrring in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course I had toyed around with websites several times over the years. The first I recall was on GeoCities and had one of those free subdomains ending in &lt;code&gt;rocks.com.xy&lt;/code&gt; or whatever. I had no clue about HTML at the time, so it consisted mainly of copyright-infringing snippets I scavenged from other pages and animated fire GIFs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So worked the wild-west that was the internet back in the nineties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also featured a &amp;ldquo;news&amp;rdquo; section. That&amp;rsquo;s what people called their blogs before they were called blogs. The websites went the way of too many briefly interesting side-projects and eventually died of neglect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then web-two-point-oh gave us a plethora of free (~beer) blog-as-a-service services. Public diaries with fancy client-side WYSIWYG editors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I resisted the hype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until that urge to have a personal, public platform came around again. That was when I caved and signed up with Blogger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;invisible-critics:2487d4758629d1c78c8e0190b9ff1261&#34;&gt;Invisible critics&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first I just welcomed the new public-ish outlet for rants. Ranting is easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also felt the urge to contribute some value to the world by sharing things I know or learn. Not that I expected many people to actually read it. However, writing forced me to structure my thoughts. To have a beginning, a middle and an end. Which turned out to be the best &lt;em&gt;and worst&lt;/em&gt; part of blogging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traffic trickled in well enough by my standards. Some of my old posts still get a good stream of visits. Mostly from web searches about problems I wrote about. A handful even hit the Hacker News front page and brought tens-of-thousands of eyeballs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put an unreasonable amount of pressure on myself to deliver value to my imaginary audience. Not only would a post have to contain a nugget of knowledge, but also live up to standards established by the popular technology blogs we all know and love - witty, to the point, well researched, properly spelled, not offensive but controversial enough to be interesting&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add to that the apparent need to maintain a &lt;a href=&#34;http://pchiusano.github.io/2014-10-11/defensive-writing&#34;&gt;defensive&lt;/a&gt; stance at all times. Hedge any claims to always have an exit in case some wise guy publicly points out all the flaws in my article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See also: &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t read the comments&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See also: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome&#34;&gt;impostor syndrome&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t Blogger&amp;rsquo;s fault - it&amp;rsquo;s in my head. Yet for me, blogging morphed from a tool for self-reflection into a stressful chore. Given that I have lots of stuff going on, it was frustrating to spend the little time I had with something I was enjoying less and less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;blogger-is-not-for-me:2487d4758629d1c78c8e0190b9ff1261&#34;&gt;Blogger is not for me.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having this virtual spotlight pointed at me - imaginary, maybe, but all the same - fed my natural urge to personalize the look and feel of my blog. Once I stepped outside the boundaries which are &lt;em&gt;themes&lt;/em&gt; I realised that Blogger is not a platform for geeks like I am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The widgets to insert functionality - such as galleries or Twitter streams - looked terrible and didn&amp;rsquo;t behave the way I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HTML and CSS I had to deal with was a mess. Multiple attempts to hand craft my own theme ended in nerd-tears. It was more tedious than I was willing to tolerate in my sparse &lt;em&gt;me time&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most canned themes looked nothing like what I wanted &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; page to look like. Dynamic layouts &lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/blog/2012/05/The-blog-gets-some-love/&#34;&gt;seemed&lt;/a&gt; neat for five minutes. Then I noticed that every Blogger blog out there looked just like mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I had a blog that wasn&amp;rsquo;t fun to write for. That didn&amp;rsquo;t look like &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;. That didn&amp;rsquo;t do what I wanted it to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;then-twitter-happened:2487d4758629d1c78c8e0190b9ff1261&#34;&gt;Then Twitter happened.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was late to the Twitter party, too. Just like I had once predicted in my first Blogger &lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/blog/2011/02/just-do-it/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reluctantly signed up during the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ndcoslo.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norwegian Developers Conference&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in 2012. There, event updates such as changes in schedule were communicated over Twitter. The way people interacted via large screens displaying live tweets hashtagged to the conference intrigued me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;This is &lt;em&gt;social&lt;/em&gt; media&amp;rdquo;, I realised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;random-five-minutes:2487d4758629d1c78c8e0190b9ff1261&#34;&gt;Random five minutes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frequent short tweets gave me an outlet for what would otherwise have built up to once-a-month blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 140 character limit took away the pressure to spend lots of time on what I publish. Yet, the subtle art of working with this limitation represented a playful challenge. The playing field was level. Nobody could make me feel bad for just throwing out a line or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brevity was not only tolerated, but a fundamental rule of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key moment was when I got an Android phone. It&amp;rsquo;s Twitter app was responsive, and - more importantly - convenient. A quick and easy way to rant or share cool stuff. It filled those random, under-utilized five minutes spread out over any given day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expressing myself via Twitter felt much more natural than what I had found myself doing on Blogger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;i-stopped-blogging-overnight:2487d4758629d1c78c8e0190b9ff1261&#34;&gt;I stopped blogging overnight.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been using Twitter more and more ever since. My twitter profile became my new online persona of choice. What blogger was supposed to be, just smaller. Unintentionally, I followed the trend from blogs to &lt;em&gt;microblogs&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s interesting is that I didn&amp;rsquo;t like Twitter more because of it&amp;rsquo;s social features. I don&amp;rsquo;t make much use of hashtags or lists or take part in discussions. In fact, I don&amp;rsquo;t think Twitter is a great tool for anything but the most superficial kind of conversation. Which are also the kinds of conversations I hate. It was the simplicity of publishing thoughts that had me hooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why try to be a full-blown author on your blog when you can just fire out one-liners on Twitter? One was much more compatible with a first-worlders daily routine than the other - I was no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;full-circle:2487d4758629d1c78c8e0190b9ff1261&#34;&gt;Full circle&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I was becoming more concerned about who owns my data online and freedom of information in general. Blogger is owned by Google, and Twitter is owned by&amp;hellip; well, Twitter. In exchange for their services, I became the product for the eyeballs they draw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hosting my online persona - micro or not - on a proprietary platform didn&amp;rsquo;t agree with my philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I was coming back full-circle to where I had begun over a decade ago when I created my first site on GeoCities. I just wanted my own little spot on the web where I can be myself. Where I can put up and take down whatever I want. And not give a damn about what anybody thinks about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this time, I know what I would have to change. I go into more depth on the goals I set for this website on &lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/project/website/&#34;&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; page. But to not make an already long post any longer, here&amp;rsquo;s the gist:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;less is more.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;
&amp;ndash; every smart person ever&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has to be simple to publish, like Twitter. Give me some room, more like Blogger. Leave me control over my content (like neither). Integrate into my worflow, with least possible friction for hosting or editing. Focus on content - no clutter such as social media integration or comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when I change my mind on any of this, I want it to be easily hackable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s see how it goes this time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>