<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Recipes on raph haXx</title>
    <link>http://raph.es/tags/recipes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Recipes on raph haXx</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Raphael Estrada 2011-2015</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2015 16:25:31 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://raph.es/tags/recipes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>LCHF Nuremberger Elisenlebkuchen</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/blog/2015/12/low-carb-high-fat-lchf-nuernberger-nuremberger-elisen-lebkuchen/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2015 16:25:31 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/blog/2015/12/low-carb-high-fat-lchf-nuernberger-nuremberger-elisen-lebkuchen/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/oldschool.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/oldschool_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;*Lebküchner* from an illustrated manuscript in the Stadtbibliothek Nürnberg, ca. 1520&#34;   /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Premium old-school *Lebkuchen* are naturally low in carbs
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lebkuchen&#34;&gt;en.wikipedia: Lebkuchen&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I&amp;rsquo;d like to share the recipe for my low-carb-high-fat (and by extension, gluten and sugar-free) variant of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.germanfoodguide.com/lebkuchen.cfm&#34;&gt;Nuremberger Elisenlebkuchen&lt;/a&gt;. You can find variations of &lt;em&gt;Lebkuchen&lt;/em&gt; all over Germany (and beyond), but the one I present here is based on an original, old-school recipe straight from the source: Nuremberg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, the best Lebkuchen are those with the highest possible nuts-to-flour ratio. This is unlike the cheaper ones you can find in supermarkets and Christmas markets all over the world, which contain more flour and sugar than nuts. The original recipes favour nuts over flour and starch; a perfectly reasonable definition of &amp;ldquo;premium&amp;rdquo; to me, and taken further, gives you the ideal LCHF treat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Src: &lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/N%C3%BCrnberger_Lebkuchen&#34;&gt;Wikipedia.de&lt;/a&gt;; Translated to English by me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Als besonderes Qualitätsmerkmal gilt ein hoher Anteil von Mandel- und Nusskernen und eine geringe Zugabe von Mehl oder sogar der völlige Verzicht darauf. [&amp;hellip;] Oblatenlebkuchen der höchsten Qualität gemäß Deutschem Lebensmittelbuch heißen „Elisenlebkuchen“ und nehmen bei praktisch allen Nürnberger Anbietern einen prominenten Platz im Sortiment ein; sie müssen eine besonders hochwertige Zusammensetzung mit mindestens 25 % Mandeln, Haselnüssen oder Walnüssen aufweisen, dürfen keine anderen Ölsamen und maximal 10 % Mehl oder 7,5 % Stärke enthalten.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A special quality characteristic is a high content of almond and nut kernels and minimal addition - or even avoidance of - flour. [&amp;hellip;] According to the German Food Guide, &amp;ldquo;Oblatenlebkuchen&amp;rdquo; of the highest quality are called &amp;ldquo;Elisenlebkuchen&amp;rdquo; and take a prominent position within the range of products offered by Nuremberg&amp;rsquo;s producers; they must have a particularly high-quality composition of at least 25 % almonds, hazelnuts or walnuts, may not contain other oilseeds and at most 10 % flour or 7.5 % starch.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing this, I cranked up the nut contents to nearly 100 % - which by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.germanfoodguide.com/lebkuchen.cfm&#34;&gt;German Food Guide&lt;/a&gt; technically qualifies as the most premium Lebkuchen one can possibly make, all the while being low in carbs and high in good fats and fibre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s only two ingredients in the original Elisen-Lebkuchen which are bad carb-offenders:
* &lt;strong&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Oblate&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;: a little tasteless wafer that holds the cake. You can just leave this out.
* &lt;strong&gt;The sugar&lt;/strong&gt;: (duh) which can easily be replaced with alternative sweeteners such as Xylitol or Stevia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/oblaten.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/oblaten_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Picture of *oblaten* wafers.&#34;   /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Oblaten are basically cardboard. Would you eat cardboard?
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;requirements:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 eggs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;200g ground raw almonds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;200g ground raw hazelnuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15g psyllium husks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Xmas-y spices (cinnamon, nutmeg, cloves, allspice, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cocoa powder (100%, unsweetened)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lemon juice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baking powder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~30g thick cut diabetic orange marmalade (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~50g Xylitol (optional) or your preferred sweenter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This yields more or less 1 large baking tray, or ~20 medium Lebkuchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;implementation:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;Implementation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, the steps are easy. It&amp;rsquo;s the spices and sweetening where I recommend you take some time and taste your way through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;short-version:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;Short version&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix nuts, eggs, psyllium husks, baking powder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add some cinnamon, cloves, cocoa, orange peel, lemon juice to taste&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sweeten using orange marmalade and/or Xylitol&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bake for 15 minutes, let cool&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;long-version:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;Long version&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-easy-bit:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;The easy bit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whisk together: nuts, eggs and psyllium husks. Add a dash of baking powder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-dash-of-christmas:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;A dash of Christmas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are Christmas treats, so add the usual suspects: cinnamon, nutmeg, cloves, anise, allspice - whatever floats your boat. I don&amp;rsquo;t mind using off-the-shelf &amp;ldquo;Christmas Spice&amp;rdquo; mixes, because I&amp;rsquo;m lazy. You can find dedicated &amp;ldquo;Lebkuchen&amp;rdquo; spice mixes, too - but those often contain sugar and wheat, so make sure you understand what you are buying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add a large spoonful of cocoa powder to the mix. Or more if you like. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t darken very much. Be careful to not add too much, it can make the dough bitter and you might find yourself adding more sweetener at the end to balance it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-orangeat-problem:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Orangeat&lt;/em&gt; problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lebkuchen&amp;rdquo; traditionally contain &lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orangeat&#34;&gt;Orangeat&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zitronat&#34;&gt;Zitronat&lt;/a&gt;, which translates to candied orange and lemon peel. This is what happens when people soak bitter food in sugar because - apparently - everything has to taste sweet in order to taste good (or so the logic seems to go).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Candied&amp;rdquo; == sugar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy you choose to sweeten your Lebkuchen depends on how sweet you like your treats to be (if at all), and then what kind of sugar alternatives you prefer. You can start off entirely un-sweet by using some actual (uncandied) orange and lemon peel, then sweeten the whole thing afterwards to taste. But be careful, you can come out on the very bitter end, which isn&amp;rsquo;t everybody&amp;rsquo;s thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;rsquo;t really go wrong with a splash or two of pure lemon juice to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I then tend to do is add one or two big spoonfuls of thick-cut diabetic orange marmalade. This adds the slightly bitter orange taste and also a bit of sweet, which I can subtract from the Xylitol I would otherwise add later. The brands I can find in my area are sweetened with sugar alcohols (Sorbitol or Maltritol), which isn&amp;rsquo;t as good as Xylitol but beats aspartame nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/marmalade.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/marmalade_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Picture of *oblaten* wafers.&#34;   /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Oblaten are basically cardboard. Would you eat cardboard?
        &lt;br/&gt;src: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stute-foods.com/itemlist.php?clasrefr=CatRef2&#34;&gt;Stute&lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I strongly recommend you take your time and gradually add very little sweet and give it a taste. Stop when it tastes sweet enough, then add a final tiny dash of sweet - the sweet taste tends to go away a bit during the baking process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However: There is no shame in err&amp;rsquo;ing on the less-sweet side. I find it more than sufficient to have the Lebkuchen only subtly sweet, leaving room for the other spices and nuts to come through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;drying-not-baking:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;Drying, not baking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put baking paper or the fancy silicon stuff onto a baking tray. Using a large spoon, distribute blobs of the dough onto the tray. Leave a bit of space between them, but don&amp;rsquo;t worry about them melting or growing much - there&amp;rsquo;s not much butter or cream in the recipe, so they should pretty much stay put.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re not going to bake these like you would a cake. Just heat them up to dry a little bit, then let &amp;lsquo;em cool. I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have to poin this out, but&amp;hellip; the longer you dry them, the drier they will be. I prefer them rather moist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stick it into the oven at 120 degrees Celsius for about 12-15 minutes. Take out the tray and let them cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/one.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/one_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Close up of one Lebkuchen I made this way.&#34;   /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a href=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/many.jpeg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://raph.es/img/blog/recipes/lebkuchen/many_thumb.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Picture of several Lebkuchen I recently made.&#34;   /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Ta-dah!
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;clearboth&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;mixing-it-up:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;Mixing it up&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional Lebkuchen contain almonds, hazelnuts and/or walnuts. But that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you can&amp;rsquo;t use other kinds! I like to use macadamia and brazil nuts. Dessicated &lt;em&gt;coconut&lt;/em&gt;, even. Go crazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, you can experiment with the spices. I recommend trying less sweetener and more cinnamon and cocoa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you so desire you can glaze them with chocolate. I usually just melt high-cocoa sugar-free chocolate with some coconut oil and spread that on top. This part is optional and up to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;references:f520193c74d3d213d7b0c492ae204cc4&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lebkuchen&#34;&gt;en.wikipedia: Lebkuchen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/N%C3%BCrnberger_Lebkuchen&#34;&gt;de.wikipedia: Nuernberger Lebkuchen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lebkuchengew%C3%BCrz&#34;&gt;de.wikipedia: Lebkuchengewuerz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;www.germanfoodguide.com/lebkuchen.cfm&#34;&gt;German Food Guide: Lebkuchen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lebkuchen-schmidt.com/en/&#34;&gt;Lebkuchen Schmidt&lt;/a&gt; - where I used to buy Lebkuchen online from abroad before I ditched carbs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LCHF bread/cake base</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/blog/2015/03/low-carb-high-fat-lchf-cake-bread/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2015 13:55:29 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/blog/2015/03/low-carb-high-fat-lchf-cake-bread/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a little recipe I use to bake breads and cakes low in carbs and high in fat - without wheat or sugar. The below describes the base which results in a bread-like loaf. By adding spices or sweetener or whatever you like you can easily modify it to your taste, including sweet cake or muffins by throwing in your sweetener of choice. You can even modify it to make pancakes, pizza dough etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most recipes for &amp;ldquo;low carb bread&amp;rdquo; you will find online try to be high in protein but low in fat. This here is my adaptation which is still medium to high in protein but also has a high fat content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;output-size:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Output size&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exact amounts depend on the size of your baking pan. I usually use a tray about 3cm deep, lined with baking paper (I prefer the re-usable silicon variant). The below makes a full oven-wide and oven-deep tray of about 2-3cm high bread/cake. You will have to try and tweak to get optimal results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nuts-and-seeds:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Nuts and seeds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The eggs and nuts are what give the bread it&amp;rsquo;s form. I use different nuts every time - whatever is around the kitchen - but they should be mostly ground (not necessarily to a flour, although that can help). You can buy them pre-ground or throw them into a food processor and gring yourself - the sky is the limit. Seeds also absorb water so they can help make the bread firm. Leave some chunky bits in if you like that. Here are just some of the things I typically throw in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;flax seed (whole or ground)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;coconut (dessicated or flour)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;chia seeds (whole)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pumpkin seeds (whole)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sunflower seeds (whole)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sesame seeds (whole)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;peanuts (chopped or ground)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;walnuts (chopped or ground)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;macadamia nuts (chopped or ground)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;brazil nuts (chopped or ground)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;psyllium husks (entire husks)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;protein-powder:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Protein powder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get good results when using protein powder to stiffen up the dough but I tend to use it lightly to not at all, nuts taste better and work fine. For smaller loafs and bread buns you might want to experiment with bigger amounts of protein powder, it helps a lot. Just make sure to get some that tastes neutral and is low in carbs, but high in protein and not full of sugar or other weird chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;ingredients:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll split this up into essential base ingredients and then list some things you can throw in to taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;base:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Base&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8-10 eggs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;100+ml whipping cream&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;100+g butter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon baking powder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20+g coconut oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;150+g various ground nuts and/or seeds (see above)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20g psyllium husks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;optional-to-taste:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Optional, to taste&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;100+g Xylitol or sweetener of choice (for sweet bread or cakes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protein powder (for firmer dough, e.g. when making buns)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peanut butter, or other nut butters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cocoa (powder or chunks)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cream cheese&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very dark chocolate (at least 85% cocoa)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One or more shots of espresso&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Berries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Salt, spices, tiny splash of vinegar (for bread variety)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grated cheese&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fried onions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bits of veggies, e.g. tomato, broccoli, cauliflower&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avocado&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;hellip;your imagination is the limit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;preparation:eaed6df6176a0d1b71e2f8de120b49bd&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not much science here, just mix it all together, maybe starting with the molten butter, eggs and cream to get them stirred up well. Add the nuts and other ingredients. You will know that the ratio of ingredients is right when the dough is a firm goo - I prefer it to still wobble and move a bit. Be careful to not make it too sticky, especially if you&amp;rsquo;re working with protein powder. Let the dough stand for at least fifteen minutes to let seeds soak and the dough to firm up. Mix a bit every now and then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pour into pan lined with baking paper (or form buns with thicker dough if that&amp;rsquo;s what you&amp;rsquo;re going for). Stick into preheated oven at around 160 degrees Celsius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the dough heats during baking, it will soften and flow together - that&amp;rsquo;s perfect for the pan, but if you want little buns and want to prevent them from becoming one large goop then make the dough stiffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bake four at least 20 minutes. Keep an eye on it every five minutes or so. Duration in oven will depend on how liquid your dough was and how high your pan is. For my pan it&amp;rsquo;s usually a bit more than 20 mins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you poke the dough and see that nothing sticks you can turn off the oven and let it stand in the remaining heat until the oven cools.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>